{
  "title": "Module 2: Sin, Grace, and Christian Vocation",
  "questions": [
    {
      "module": 2.1,
      "section": "Sin frustrates human fulfillment by preventing the realization of substantive goods, such as when:",
      "question": "Knowing persistence in sin can harm the good of health by engendering anxiety, depression, changes in sleep patterns or appetite, etc.",
      "choices": {
        "A": "Sinful choices gain social acceptance, shifting conventional perceptions of good and evil, and thereby obscuring the knowledge of truth.",
        "B": "One sins for any reason, since \"sin\" is nothing other than wrongdoing insofar as it disrupts the good of religion, i.e. harmony with God.",
        "C": "Option 1 and Option 2",
        "D": 4
      },
      "correctAnswer": ""
    },
    {
      "module": 2.1,
      "section": "Sin frustrates human fulfillment by preventing the realization of existential goods, such as when:\r",
      "question": "A conscience burdened by the knowledge of sin cannot rejoice in the pleasures of life, such as good food, music, or conversation.\r",
      "choices": {
        "A": "Those in a state of grave sin cannot validly contract marriage, which embodies qualities of both existential and substantive goods.\r",
        "B": "Integrity is damaged as a result of sinful choices and the rationalizations made to mitigate the inner tension resulting from them.\r",
        "C": "Option 1 and Option 2.\r",
        "D": 3
      },
      "correctAnswer": ""
    },
    {
      "module": 2.1,
      "section": "In a Catholic perspective, sin offends God in the sense that:",
      "question": "God experiences anger and resentment at betrayal in the same way that humans do.",
      "choices": {
        "A": "Our sins deprive God of mana, or the psychic energy whence his divine power derives.",
        "B": "Our sins subvert God's wise and loving plan for us, thereby wounding him in his image.",
        "C": "All of the above",
        "D": 3
      },
      "correctAnswer": "See FC, pp. 154-155."
    },
    {
      "module": 2.1,
      "section": "The Old Testament presents sin under different aspects, such as:",
      "question": "A failure of creativity or self-assertion against the coercive forces exerted through established social norms.",
      "choices": {
        "A": "A free, self-determining choice to reject God's offer of grace and friendship, mediated through Jesus Christ.",
        "B": "An abuse of human freedom, rooted in a willful rebellion against God, which distorts the sinner's inner being.",
        "C": "All of the above",
        "D": 3
      },
      "correctAnswer": "See FC, pp. 149-150, 154-155."
    },
    {
      "module": 2.1,
      "section": "Guilt is not primarily a psychological phenomenon, since:",
      "question": "Sin, being a disruption of our relationship with God, is a spiritual phenomenon with no bearing on bodily health.",
      "choices": {
        "A": "Sin presupposes choice, and choices determine the one who chooses even if he or she is not troubled by them.",
        "B": "Guilt is primarily a sociological phenomenon, indicating ascription to an out-group due to antisocial behavior.",
        "C": "None of the above",
        "D": 2
      },
      "correctAnswer": "(See FC, pp. 152-153)"
    },
    {
      "module": 2.1,
      "section": "In a Catholic perspective, grave sin is inevitable without faith, hope, and charity, since:",
      "question": "Grace enables us to see how everything a Christian does contributes to God's glory, even sin.",
      "choices": {
        "A": "Many sins are born out of despair at the prospect of achieving lasting happiness in this world.",
        "B": "The promise of salvation is a form of social control, discouraging antisocial behavior (Ie., sin).",
        "C": "None of the above",
        "D": 2
      },
      "correctAnswer": "True, all will glorify God, whether in his mercy or in his justice. But, '\"As I live; declares the Lord, 'I do not desire the death of the sinner, but that he be converted and saved\"' (Ez. 33:11; cf. Lk. 15). This statement evokes the argument for proportionalism predicated on God's power to draw good from evil, presented and debunked in chapter 6 (see FC, p. 67). "
    },
    {
      "module": 2.1,
      "section": "In a Catholic perspective, sin has a social dimension in the sense that:",
      "question": "Standards of good and evil are culturally conditioned, hence lacking universal applicability.",
      "choices": {
        "A": "God inflicts temporal punishments upon entire communities for the sins of their members.",
        "B": "The acceptance of sinful behavior at a social level obscures moral truth, conducing to sin.",
        "C": "None of the above",
        "D": 3
      },
      "correctAnswer": "See FC, p. 158. "
    },
    {
      "module": 2.1,
      "section": "The New Testament enriched the biblical understanding of sin by drawing attention to:",
      "question": "The nature of sin as an unjustified and ungrateful rejection of God's love for humanity (Rom. 5:8).",
      "choices": {
        "A": "The necessity of keeping the whole of the Mosaic Law as a condition of righteousness (Deut. 8:1-6).",
        "B": "The external violation of a commandment, irrespective of intent, as the essence of sin (Num. 4:15).",
        "C": "Option 1 and Option 2",
        "D": 1
      },
      "correctAnswer": "This is the only New Testament citation among the three options. "
    },
    {
      "module": 2.1,
      "section": "Because sin always involves a choice:",
      "question": "Genuinely irrational or compulsive behavior, e.g., due to mental illness, is not to be reckoned sinful.",
      "choices": {
        "A": "Ceasing sinful behavior is necessary but not sufficient for reversing the moral identity of a sinner.",
        "B": "Only those who choose finite human goods over the infinite goodness of God can be called sinners.",
        "C": "Option 1 and Option 2",
        "D": 4
      },
      "correctAnswer": ""
    },
    {
      "module": 2.1,
      "section": "In a Catholic perspective, sin has the character of a privation in the sense that sinners lack:",
      "question": "Social acceptance, hence the imperative to construct an inclusive, morally permissive society.",
      "choices": {
        "A": "The assistance of God's grace, without which sin is inevitable and with which it is impossible.\r\n",
        "B": "An upright conscience, their choices being in disagreement with their knowledge of moral truth.\r\n",
        "C": "All of the above.\r",
        "D": 3
      },
      "correctAnswer": ""
    },
    {
      "module": 2.2,
      "section": "According to Grisez, \"light matter\" should be understood as:",
      "question": "Circumstances lessening one's responsibility for committing an objectively serious sin.",
      "choices": {
        "A": "Moral wrongdoing which is not in conflict with faith or its consequent responsibilities.",
        "B": "The external violation of a moral norm, irrespective of intent, and its consequences.",
        "C": "None of the above",
        "D": 2
      },
      "correctAnswer": "While subjective factors such as the mental toll of stress or extreme emotion may render an otherwise mortal sin merely venial, such factors cannot alter the objective gravity of the sin itself. To illustrate, murder is always gravely wrong because it involves direct hostility to the good of human life, but murders in \"hot\" blood (Le., crimes of passion, such as a man who kills another man he caught having sex with his wife) do not involve the same premeditation as those in \"cold\" blood (Le., lying in ambush to kill an enemy), and are less imputable to malice.\n\nSee FC, pp. 189, 192. "
    },
    {
      "module": 2.2,
      "section": "The Catholic theological tradition identifies grave sins with choices which are incompatible with:",
      "question": "Membership in the Church as a human society, such as murder and adultery.",
      "choices": {
        "A": "A relationship of faith with God, such as idolatry, apostasy, or blasphemy.",
        "B": "A will toward integral human fulfillment; that is, all sins are grave per se.",
        "C": "Option 1 and Option 2",
        "D": 4
      },
      "correctAnswer": "See FC, pp. 189-191. "
    },
    {
      "module": 2.2,
      "section": "Proponents of a revisionist theory of the fundamental option, such as Karl Rahner, maintain that our discrete choices:",
      "question": "Have only the appearance of being truly free, when in fact they are determined by the forces of instinct and socialization.",
      "choices": {
        "A": "Provide evidence about our relationship with God, but cannot tell us definitively whether we have a basic openness to him.",
        "B": "Directly shape our moral life and confer upon us the identity of a person open or closed to a loving relationship with God.",
        "C": "All of the above",
        "D": 2
      },
      "correctAnswer": "Revisionists do maintain that our discrete choices are less than fully free, though they are not deterministic as this option implies. Rather, they say discrete choices are not fully determinative because prior ones determine the possibilities available for those that follow. Thus they postulate the existence of a hypothetical absolute or transcendental freedom, Le., a \"fundamental option\" directly for or against God, exercised unconsciously at the core of one's being."
    },
    {
      "module": 2.2,
      "section": "According to its critics, difficulties with the revisionist theory of the fundamental option include its implication that:",
      "question": "It is possible to knowingly choose in ways incompatible with the commitment of faith without thereby becoming a morally bad person.",
      "choices": {
        "A": "All of a person's choices should be in accord with the ideal of integral human fulfillment for him or her to be reckoned morally good.",
        "B": "Supernatural charity is lost not only through the direct rejection of God, but through every grave sin committed knowingly and freely.",
        "C": "Option 1 and Option 2",
        "D": 1
      },
      "correctAnswer": "See FC, p. 194."
    },
    {
      "module": 2.2,
      "section": "In a Catholic perspective, non-Christians can be guilty of grave sin:",
      "question": "If they refuse to seek membership in the Church despite judging it to be necessary for their salvation.",
      "choices": {
        "A": "If they deliberately choose acts which are incompatible with membership in any human community.",
        "B": "By the simple fact of their estrangement from God and the community of faith which he founded.",
        "C": "Option 1 and Option 2",
        "D": 4
      },
      "correctAnswer": "See FC, p. 190; cf. FC, ch. 3, regarding the normativity of judgments of conscience. "
    },
    {
      "module": 2.2,
      "section": "According to Grisez, a strength of the revisionist theory of the fundamental option is that it:",
      "question": "Rightly identifies the foreseen good and bad outcomes of a choice as the basis for reckoning its moral quality.",
      "choices": {
        "A": "Provides an alternative to authoritative teaching, to ease the consciences of those burdened by inordinate guilt.",
        "B": "Introduces the notion of self-commitment into moral theology, instead of focusing inordinately on isolated acts.",
        "C": "All of the above",
        "D": 3
      },
      "correctAnswer": "See FC, p. 193. "
    },
    {
      "module": 2.2,
      "section": "According to Grisez, the act of faith is the fundamental option of a Christian in the sense that:",
      "question": "It organizes the believer's life, whereby he or she commits to follow Jesus and be like him, while also avoiding all things to the contrary.",
      "choices": {
        "A": "The one thing necessary for salvation is to profess faith in Jesus Christ (Rom. 10:9); all other doctrines are superfluous human inventions.",
        "B": "One can never know with certitude whether he or she has genuinely accepted Jesus or instead merely honors him outwardly (Mt. 15:8).",
        "C": "All of the above",
        "D": 1
      },
      "correctAnswer": "See FC, pp. 188-189."
    },
    {
      "module": 2.2,
      "section": "Grisez writes that those who try to live uprightly often reach a point where they have few morally significant choices to make. By this, he means that:",
      "question": "God's law stifles creativity and restricts human freedom, inhibiting people from pursuing goods they would otherwise find fulfilling.\r",
      "choices": {
        "A": "The only truly significant choice is whether to accept or to reject a relationship with God, that is, to accept or to reject faith.",
        "B": "Such people have formed a good character, with the result that their daily routine reflects and expresses their basic commitments.",
        "C": "None of the above\r",
        "D": 3
      },
      "correctAnswer": ""
    },
    {
      "module": 2.2,
      "section": "According to Grisez, Catholics who willfully do what the Church teaches is gravely wrong:\r",
      "question": "Sin lightly, since many things the Church teaches to be gravely wrong do not seriously harm physical or mental well-being.\r",
      "choices": {
        "A": "Do not sin, since morality is a personal construct and no one can be bound by moral norms she has not chosen to follow.\r",
        "B": "Sin gravely, since their rejection of the Church's authority is incompatible with being a faithful member of its communion. \r\n",
        "C": "Option 1 and Option 2\r",
        "D": 3
      },
      "correctAnswer": ""
    },
    {
      "module": 2.2,
      "section": " The Council of Trent taught definitively that one cannot know with the certitude of faith whether one is in the state of grace. From this, it follows that:\r",
      "question": "None of the above\r",
      "choices": {
        "A": "Our consciences can be mistaken about the state of our souls, notwithstanding our basic capacity to know whether we have sinned. \r\n",
        "B": "We can never know whether we are basically good or bad people, though our discrete choices can offer some evidence in this area.\r",
        "C": "We are not responsible for our choices, including ostensible sins, since we cannot know moral truth with any degree of certitude.\r",
        "D": 2
      },
      "correctAnswer": ""
    },
    {
      "module": 2.5,
      "section": "An example of the \"meekness\" involved in the second mode of Christian response (MCR2) could be:",
      "question": "A priest who delegates the pastoral care of the sick in his parish to laypersons, so that he can focus on administrative work:",
      "choices": {
        "A": "A man whose wife left him for another man, who is now contemplating civil marriage to another woman he has been dating.",
        "B": "A woman who, thinking the prohibition on women's ordination unjust, conceals her sex to gain admission to the seminary.",
        "C": "None of the above",
        "D": 4
      },
      "correctAnswer": "\"Meekness becomes explicit in one who finds and accepts his or her personal vocation and lives contentedly within its boundaries...Lack of meekness is apparent in one who is frustrated and resentful over the duties and limits of his or her state of life and vocation;\" see FC, 307. Although separated, spouses remain bound by important moral obligations toward one another. This includes the obligation of keeping faith, which precludes new romantic or sexual relationships, including remarriage (see LL 16:18).\n\n\"Meekness is...lacking in a Church in which some lay people want to function as if they were priests, [and] some priests as if they were lay people;\" see FC, p. 307. Administrative work is incidental to a priest's vocation and pastoral charge, not central. Qualified laypersons (e.g., accountants, engineers, attorneys) can assist priests in carrying out this work, which does not require the power of orders conferred by means of the sacrament of ordination. "
    },
    {
      "module": 2.5,
      "section": "An example of the \"mourning\" involved in the third mode of Christian response (MCR3) could be:",
      "question": "A successful businessman who, discerning a call to priesthood, gives up his career in order to enter seminary formation.",
      "choices": {
        "A": "A seminarian who discerns out of formation after several years, despite a strong inclination for service in the Church.",
        "B": "A mother who refuses to help fund her son's seminary education, since she believes he will not be happy as a priest.",
        "C": "Option 1 and Option 2",
        "D": 4
      },
      "correctAnswer": "See FC, p. 308"
    },
    {
      "module": 2.5,
      "section": "Darwin (born Winnie) was dismissed from his parish's ministry of lectors after coming out as transgender. Modes of Christian Response potentially relevant to his personal vocation may include:",
      "question": "MCR3, inasmuch as continued membership in a non-affirming church is a needless hardship, avoidable through Christian detachment.",
      "choices": {
        "A": "MCR6, inasmuch as Darwin should suppress his feelings and keep silent for the sake of the peace of the parish in humble resignation.",
        "B": "MCR4, inasmuch as continued membership in a non-affirming church is a necessary hardship, to be borne with Christian fortitude.",
        "C": "None of the above",
        "D": 3
      },
      "correctAnswer": "Christ founded the Catholic Church and proposed membership in it as a means to salvation; see Jn. 6:68. Rejection by one's fellow believers is indeed a hardship of the sort which would strongly tempt someone in Darwin's situation to leave the Catholic Church, or the practice of religion altogether. While the Lord Jesus gravely censures those who give scandal (Le., undermining the faith of others; see Mt. 18:6), nonetheless he desires that all be saved; see Ezek. 33:11.\n\nMCR7 is also relevant to this situation. Hostility and sinfulness among one's fellow believers does not nullify the role of the Church in our spiritual lives, for we, too, are conscious of our sinfulness and need for God's mercy. See Nit. 18:21-35, in which the Lord Jesus commands us to forgive our fellow believers who sin against us and illustrates this by a parable."
    },
    {
      "module": 2.5,
      "section": "MCR7 (\"peacemaking\") goes beyond its corresponding mode of responsibility (MR7), in that:",
      "question": "Mere fairness is not enough to achieve justice and repair relationships; therefore, Christians should imitate Christ's example of mercy.",
      "choices": {
        "A": "The great good of salvation outweighs the harm caused by the use of violence; therefore, Christians may engage in coercive proselytism.",
        "B": "Merely tolerating our enemies falls short of the standards Christ modeled for us by seeking to restore sinners to the friendship of God.",
        "C": "None of the above",
        "D": 3
      },
      "correctAnswer": "See Mt. 5:38-40; Rom. 5:8; Lk. 23:34; 1 Pet. 3:9. \n\nIf option 3: That's MCR 5, not MCR7."
    },
    {
      "module": 2.5,
      "section": "Patricia is a Catholic in a stable, romantic, domestic relationship with another woman. Modes of Christian Response potentially relevant to her personal vocation may include:",
      "question": "MCR7, inasmuch as she should be ready to meet unfair criticism of her relationship not with hostility, but with a spirit of forgiveness.",
      "choices": {
        "A": "MCR2, inasmuch as her orientation excludes a vocation to marriage, which the Catholic Church teaches to be intrinsically heterosexual.",
        "B": "MRC5, inasmuch as she should bear patiently with her partner, be attentive to her needs, and go beyond mere fairness in caring for her.",
        "C": "All of the above",
        "D": 4
      },
      "correctAnswer": "Unfair criticism in this context would include baseless suppositions, e.g., that Patricia had fallen away from the Catholic faith because of her relationship, that her partner was a bad influence upon heq or that the relationship is sexual in nature merely because the parties are lesbians. None of these need be the case and should not be assumed (e.g., the fact of a man and a woman dating is not grounds to infer they are sexually active, so it seems unfair to draw this conclusion from the fact of two men or two women being in a similar relationship).\n\nFair criticism should always be considered thoughtfully, in a spirit of humility. If, for example, the aforesaid suppositions were grounded in evidence, or if the relationship were abusive, then it would be wrong not to pay heed."
    },
    {
      "module": 2.5,
      "section": "An example of the \"mercy\" involved in the fifth mode of Christian response (MCR5) could be:",
      "question": "All of the above",
      "choices": {
        "A": "A wife who consents to her husband's adultery, since it is clear how much happier he is with the other woman than he is with her.",
        "B": "A nurse who gives a patient a lethal dose of morphine, judging this to be the lesser evil relative to letting her suffer interminably.",
        "C": "A student who walks to campus instead of taking the trike, so that he can give his pamasahe to a mahihirap he meets along the way.",
        "D": 4
      },
      "correctAnswer": "But mercy means far more than just forgiving others; it means striving generously to do them good, and doing so universally and as perfectly as possible, without\ncalculating the cost to oneself; FC, p. 310."
    },
    {
      "module": 2.5,
      "section": "An example of the \"poverty of spirit\" involved in the first mode of Christian response (MCR1) could be:",
      "question": "A man who fervently thanks God for making him zealous and righteous, in contrast to those who are \"Christians in name only.\"",
      "choices": {
        "A": "A woman who receives a terminal cancer diagnosis and prays to God for a cure, \"or if it be not Your will, then a peaceful death:'",
        "B": "A woman who puts off going to confession because she knows God could never forgive sins as numerous and grave as her own.",
        "C": "All of the above",
        "D": 2
      },
      "correctAnswer": "\"Humility consists in seeking everything from God, accepting all that he gives, and being fully aware and grateful for it...And with humility, Christian life becomes authentically Eucharistic - a grateful response to God's gift of justification and adoption;\" see FC, p. 306; cf. job 2:10."
    },
    {
      "module": 2.5,
      "section": "An example of the \"hunger and thirst for righteousness\" involved in the fourth mode of Christian response (MCR4) could be:",
      "question": "A student who stops her university studies to join an insurgent group, taking up arms to overthrow structures of imperialist oppression.\r",
      "choices": {
        "A": "A divorcee who converts from Catholicism to Aglipayanism so that she will be able to remarry and receive holy communion once more.\r",
        "B": "A woman who converts to Catholicism, knowing that her Protestant relatives will oppose this decision and try to dissuade her from it.\r",
        "C": "Option 1 and Option 2\r",
        "D": 3
      },
      "correctAnswer": ""
    },
    {
      "module": 2.5,
      "section": "MCR8 (\"compassion\") goes beyond its corresponding mode of responsibility (MR8), in that:",
      "question": "Conscious of sin's power and the need for grace, Christians see that all human activity is tainted by evil and that good is unattainable.",
      "choices": {
        "A": "Christian life involves sacrifice because human goods detract from heavenly fulfillment and therefore must be avoided assiduously.",
        "B": "All can see that evil should not be done for the sake of good, but Christians see that good must be done even if they will suffer for it.",
        "C": "All of the above",
        "D": 3
      },
      "correctAnswer": ""
    }
  ]
}